Okay, so let's talk about some additional
terms then, some other interpersonal and
team skills that's really necessary to
engage, motivate, lead your team.
Now, some of these terms, though, they've
been covered in other
videos as well, right?
Because they span a few topics,
right, such as the first one here,
active listening.
This is something that we already covered
in the communication section.
An active listen really refers to
basically communication.
Remember, communication is not just about
words.
Communication is also about pitch and
tone, body language.
Words are only a small part of
communication.
And when you are communicating, communication
is not just about speaking either.
Part of communication is also listening.
Just talking and talking and talking and
talking.
talking, talking over somebody else,
that's not good communication.
When somebody else
is trying to talk and you're
talking over them, that's
actually bad communication.
That's not good communication at all.
Part of communication is also listening.
A good communicator will always be a good
listener.
Now, an extension of listening is
something called active listening.
An active listening basically
means going one step
further and giving
feedback back to the center.
remember the sender receiver model you
have a sender sending a message to the
receiver and then the receiver giving
feedback back to the sender right so part
of communication is giving feedback and
feedback is considered active listening
part of communication is listening and
active listening where you're actually
giving feedback back to the send now the
feedback can be in the form of repeating
the message or it could be in the form of
you know nodding your head in a shaking
your head in disagreement,
you know, there's
many different ways of giving feedback.
Now, when it comes to active listening,
there are three forms, right, three forms
of active listening, three forms,
if like, of giving feedback.
Right, reflecting, attending, and then
following.
Right, so reflecting.
Reflecting basically refers to repeating
the message.
Like as, for example, somebody gives you a
phone number and you
repeat it back to them.
Right, you're writing down someone's phone
number and then you'll repeat it back.
Right, that's known as reflecting,
repeating the message.
Or think of air traffic control.
Air traffic control sends a message to the
pilot.
The pilot responds back by repeating the
exact same message, let for letter,
number for number, word for word,
back to air traffic control.
Repeating the message or
reflecting also involves situations
such as, let's say you have
been given some instructions.
so your manager gives
you some instructions
and you repeat the
instruction back to them.
Just to make sure you've understood.
I mean, you know, we do that all the time.
I just making sure.
So hangar you, it'll be like a case of,
you know, okay, so let me just repeat what
you just said just so that I can
understand, just so that I've understood
what you just said, just so that I don't
make a mistake.
So you just repeat the message back to
them.
Right, so that would be known as
reflecting.
Another type then of active listening,
right, is something called attending.
And attending basically
means that the other
person knows that you're
actually listening, right?
The other person knows that you're
actually attentive.
And, you know, you're not just,
you know, staring into space or you're
thinking of something else or,
you know, you, you know, the other person
knows that you are actually attentive
there.
So things like maintaining eye contact,
refraining from doing.
other work, not just checking his cell
phone while the other person is talking,
you know, that kind of thing.
Right.
Now, when we say maintaining eye contact,
I mean, maintaining eye contact,
but without staring, I mean, you know,
if you're staring at someone that's going
to creep them out, but that's not what
attending a cell phone refers to,
it refers to, you don't
maintain eye contact,
just like when you're
in an interview, right?
You have to maintain eye
contact with whoever is you're
interviewing with, but
you're not staring at them.
And then another type of active listening
is following and then following means just
responding back in non-verbal gestures
like nodding your head in disagreement
right shaking your head in disagreement
right so that's a type of non-verbal but
it doesn't have to be non-verbal right
also things like asking questions
following up right they're asking you're
having a conversation and you're just
asking questions right so they're just
like say you're sitting in a class the
instructor is is teaching you and you want
to clarify a point, you ask questions.
So that way the instructor knows that you
are actively listening, right?
So these are the three components of
active listening, reflecting, attending,
following.
Now, another key interpersonal skill,
communication styles assessment.
Again, this is a part of communication.
You need to adjust your communication
style accordingly.
and a good leader will always be someone
that can communicate.
Remember, good leader is always a good
communicator.
Project manager is always good
You need to communicate.
So you're going to adjust your
communication style accordingly.
Now, according to who
you're communicating with, and
most of us do that to some
extent, at least anyway.
You communicate very, very differently to
your senior executives in your
organization then you do to junior team
members, for example.
Communication style is going to be very
different.
And so expand that to all stakeholders
now.
So based on personal differences,
political differences, cultural
differences, background, right,
as in a technical person, are they within
the organization, are the outside of the
organization?
Obviously, if you've got team members
within your organization, you're going to
be using more technical language,
more company-specific language,
acronyms and so and so forth to have a
discussion and describe problems,
describe issues, and so and so forth.
If there's somebody outside of your
organization, you start using those
company-specific acronyms, they'll have no
idea what you're talking about.
So again, you're going to be adjusting
your communication style accordingly.
You're going to adjust your communication
to the audience.
And then another term that, again,
we've covered in actually a couple of
places a couple of videos, nominal group
technique.
A normal group
technique is a extension, if
you like, or a continuation
of a brainstorming.
In a brainstorming, you come up with all
of your different ideas, in a normal group
technique, you discuss those ideas,
you vote, and then you rank those ideas.
Now, along with this,
I want to talk a little
bit about personality profile assessments.
Everybody is different.
Everyone has their own personality.
And based on that, you're going to
communicate then.
Again, a leader is going to communicate
differently depending on your personality.
So for the exam, you may come across this
personality profile assessment.
You just need to know that
these are the different types
of personality profile
assessments that are out there.
I mean, there's many out there, but these
are just some of the more common ones.
So you want to assess,
determine the best way to
communicate, work with
different personality types.
Right.
So, you know, some team
members or some team, some of
you guys may have done a
personality profile assessment.
Just basically is really nothing more than
just a whole bunch of questions.
It's just a lot of, essentially,
it's like a questionnaire.
And then based on how
you answer those questions,
they will determine what
kind of personality you have.
Right, what kind of personality traits you
have.
And a couple of the common ones are these
Myers-Briggs type syndicator, right,
MBTI.
You've got this one called the Social
Style by TRACOM, whole brain thinking,
theory of psychological types.
Disc assessment is a common one.
And then this last one here, true color.
So these are just some of the more common
ones.
And, you know, a lot of
times you might also see
this during interviews
or before an interview.
Again, they'll give you a whole bunch of
questions and you want to, basically,
they want to assess your personality type.
Will you fit into this team?
Will you be better off in another team?
Which team will you fit in?
Which organization,
as in, you know, internal,
especially say before you
go for an interview, right?
They want to see which team to put you in,
which department to put you in.
So some of the, doing
some of these personality
profile assessments can help with that.
And then generally as well, within you.
your team within your organization.
You can see your own
personality profile, see your own
personality type and see what
kind of personality you want to be.
And then you can see how you want to,
there are what changes you need to make,
what improvements you need
to make to, you know, become
the kind of manager or the
leader that you want to be.
So anyway, these are
just a couple of examples of
different types of personality
profile assessments.